Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is דף נ"ג daf
Nun Gimmel and we are moving on in איזהו מקומן, Eizehu Mekoman,
the פרק perek that we, some of us at least, when we
wake up on time, say in דאוונען davening every morning. Somebody told
me once that that was his special מצות היום mitzas hayom for
שבועות Shavuos is to say איזהו מקומן Eizehu Mekoman because you're up
all night so you can actually say it. Anyway,
and we're doing the general חטאות, chata'os, the outer חטאות, chata'os, and
the משנה Mishnah describes how it was done in the north, with
applications on all four corners. The remnant of the blood that spilled
at the base. The base here is going to be the south
base, not the west base. We will get to that. The inner
חטאות chata'os that spilled at the west base. And that you go
up the מזבח mizbe'ach and you go counterclockwise because you're always turning
to the right with your face towards the center. That's also how
the כלה kallah goes around the חתן. chosson. That's also how we
take out the ספר תורה Sefer Torah and put it back from
the ארון aron and so on. Okay, and would be eaten by
male כהנים Kohanim in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So now let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Top of נ"ג עמוד א',
nun gimmel amud aleph, about six lines down. היכי עביד? Heichi Ofid?
How exactly would they place it at the corner of the altar,
the blood? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar.
חד אמר, Chad amar, נותן nosein אמה אילך ואמה אילך. amah eilech
v'amah eilech. If you think about the corner here, here's my little
picture, right? And the corner looks like the horns, as it were,
on the top of the altar, right? That's what the horns would
look like. You have the top of the altar,
okay, and you have an אמה amah by an אמה amah at
each corner which would be the horns. Okay, and the כהן Kohen
would be standing like down here, he'd be walking on the walkaround.
Okay, and these are the horns. So one opinion says, you put
it anywhere on the horn. You could put it an אמה amah
in this direction or an אמה amah in that direction. That's considered,
and then you do that for all four horns. You don't necessarily
have to do it at the edge, exactly
where it hits
the corner itself, anywhere basically on that horn would count. Okay, so
אמה אילך ואמה אילך. amah eilech v'amah eilech. Maybe I'll do the
blood in, I don't have red, but I'll use orange. An אמה
amah on either side, that would be fine for the horn. Not
both, either
or. Okay. So חד אמר, Chad amar, נותן nosein אמה אילך ואמה
אילך. amah eilech v'amah eilech. And the other says,
מחטא ויורד כנגד חודו של קרן. mechatei v'yored k'neged chodo shel keren.
No, you're sort of,
יורד yored is a downward direction. The word מחטא mechatei is just
a verb from the word חטא, chata, okay? מחטא אותה Mechatei osah
is based on the verse. Who makes it into a חטאת. Chatas.
Okay, so it means that you would apply the blood by actually
at the corner
itself in a downward motion. The primary reason you would do a
downward motion is so that you wouldn't get your garments all bloody
anyways. So you start up and you move down anyway, it would
be over there. Okay. So that's the debate. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, אליבא דרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון aliba d'Rabbi Elazar
b'Rabbi Shimon דאמר היא עצמה אינה נעשית אלא בגופה של קרן. d'amar
hi atzmah ninasah ela b'gufo shel keren. Now we're going to see
in a minute that there's a debate of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon and רבי Rebbi which is whether it has
to be at the horn itself, which is the פשט, pshat, or
can it really
be anywhere following the horn down the side of the
altar? Okay, so can it actually be
here? Let me erase this for now to get it out of
the way. Okay, so if this is the walkaround here, the סובב,
soveiv, and could it be, could he apply it, I mean the
סובב soveiv would actually be
four אמות amos I think, anyway three
אמות. amos. So it'd sort of be like this. Okay, anyway, so
does it have to be here at the horn or can it
actually be anywhere going down actually opposite the horn? If you imagine
the horn would like pierce through, could it actually be
anywhere the height of the altar, at least in this top section,
going down from the space of the horn? Okay, so that's the
question. So רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon would say
it had to be at the horn itself. רבי Rebbi would say
it could actually be directly below the horn anywhere at that edge
of the altar. Is that picture clear? You see what I'm sort
of describing there? All right. Yeah. Okay, so אליבא דרבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון aliba d'Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon דאמר היא עצמה אינה נעשית אלא
בגופה של קרן d'amar hi atzmah ninasah ela b'gufo shel keren כולי
עלמא לא פליגי. kulei alma lo pligi. Nobody debates, meaning as long
as you're doing it on the horn itself, of course you could
do it anywhere on the horn. Why should it have to be
at the edge of the horn? So anywhere here would be fine.
Everybody would agree to that. So what's the debate? The debate is
if you're doing it below the horn. What is still considered to
be the קרן, keren, the corner? Would you say any space opposite
the, any space going straight down, even here? Or no, only once
you're not on the horn itself, if you're doing it below the
horn to be considered the קרן. keren. which also means like the
horn, the corner, the edge, you'd have to do it at the
edge itself. איפלגי אליביה דרבי. Ipalligi alibei de-Rabbi. מר סבר אמה אילך
ואמה אילך כנגד קרן Mar savar ama eilech va-ama eilech kenegged Keren
and an ama each direction directly below the horn counts as the
horn. ומר סבר U-mar savar and the other holds כנגד חודה אין
טפי לא. Kenegged huda in tfei lo. No, it has to only
be right at the edge itself. If you're not doing it on
the horn itself to be considered that you placed it at the
קרן, Keren, at the corner, okay? So the corner here would not
just be you could draw an imaginary line and say, well, anywhere
an ama in either direction is still part of the corner. No,
to be defined as the corner when you're not on the horn,
it would have to be at the edge itself. Okay, that's a
reasonable debate. Okay, מיתיבי. Meitivei. Now let me challenge this idea that
it doesn't have to be the edge, that it could actually be
an ama in either direction. חטאת הציבור והיחיד. Chatat hatzibbur vehayachid.
Here we have a ברייתא. Braita. The communal and the individual חטאות.
Chattaot. כיצד? Keitzad? How would you do it? כיצד מתן דמן? Keitzad
mattan daman? How would you put their blood? היה עולה בכבש, Haya
oleh bakkivish, you'd go up the ramp, ופנה לסובב, Ufana lasovev, and
you go to the סובב, Sovev, the walk-around, okay? ובא לו לקרן
דרומית מזרחית. Uva lo lekeren dromit mizrachit. You come here to the,
so presumably right, let's assume that you know here's the ramp actually,
whatever, I'm not going to draw the ramp getting in the way.
But anyway, here you came up. This would be the, this is
the east, this is the north, this is the south, okay? Here's
where you came up on your ramp. You come here, okay, and
you start with the southeast and you're going to go around. Okay,
so ובא לו לקרן דרומית מזרחית, Uva lo lekeren dromit mizrachit, southeast
corner. וטובל באצבעו הימנית המיומנת שבימין. Vetovel be'etzba'o hayemanit hamiyumenet shebiyamin. You
dip with your right hand, the rightest of the right, I don't
know how many right hands you have. So Rashi says מיומנת Miyumenet
means like the most dexterous, the most, you know, sort of like
powerful, mainly basically means your pointer finger, the one that's the most
effective. Okay, so you dip with your right finger, your right pointer
finger, מן הדם שבמזרק, Min hadam shebammizrak, into the blood that's in
the bowl, וחומר בגודלו מלמעלה ובאצבעו קטנה מלמטה. Vechomer begodlo milma'la uve'etzba'o
ketana milmata.
And you are חומר Chomer with your thumb and your pinky. What
does חומר Chomer mean? So Rashi says what the word חומר Chomer
means is, is that it means like you sort of like you
scrape the blood. So if you dip your finger in and you're
going to be like now applying it, you're going to use your
thumb, I don't know how you're supposed to use your pinky, you
have to be quite dexterous. But anyway, you like use your thumb
to make sure like you know pushing the blood alongside your pointer
finger, make sure that it all comes off of your finger as
you're applying it. That's what Rashi says. Rambam says what it means
is you support your pointer finger with your thumb. Okay, anyway, so
you use your thumb and your pinky to assist, ומחטא ויורד כנגד
חודה
של קרן. Umchate veyored
kenegged huda shel keren.
And you apply the blood going downward opposite the actual corner of
the horn. עד שמכלה כל הדם שבאצבעו. Ad shemechale kol hadam shebe'etzba'o.
Okay, until you, until you use up all the blood on your
finger, you get it all on the horn, וכן כל קרן וקרן.
Vechen kol keren vekeren. And similarly by every corner. So basically it
explicitly says opposite the corner of the horn. So there goes the
argument that it could be an ama in either direction. It says
explicitly on the corner of the horn. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer
is הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar. מצוה בחודה אי עביד אמה אילך ואמה
אילך לית לן בה. Mitzvah bechuda i avid ama eilech va-ama eilech
leit lan bah. No, the one that says an ama each side
concedes that it's the ideally should be at the corner itself, at
the edge itself. So that's why the ברייתא Braita describes it to
be on the corner, on the edge. Everybody agrees that's the ideal.
The question is, is it also acceptable if you do it an
ama on each direction? Okay, now by the way, what's also not
clear is, before we said everybody agrees it's acceptable an ama each
direction if you're at the horn itself. Would even the horn itself
we say the ideal is to be at the very edge, you
know, it sounds like it from this ברייתא. Braita. Okay, so what
we're saying is the ideal is to be at the literally at
the at the edge there of the horn or directly or below
the horn according to רבי. Rabbi. Okay, but בדיעבד, Bedi'avad, but it
works if it's an ama on each side certainly on the horn
itself. The question is does it work if it's an ama on
each side directly below the horn? Okay, and that was what was
being debated. So now let's continue. מאי רבי ומאי רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון? Mai Rabbi u-mai Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon? What is this debate
of רבי Rabbi and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון? Rabbi Elazar berabi Shimon?
Whether it has to be the horn or whether it could be
the area directly below the horn. וברבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון דתניא, Uve-Rabbi
Elazar berabi Shimon detanya, for it's taught in a ברייתא. Braita. דמים
העליונים ניתנים מחוט הסיקרא ולמעלה. Damim ha'elyonim nitanim mechut hasikra ulema'la.
So the above bloods would be from the red line and above.
Okay, the red line is the line that would go through the
middle of the
altar. And דמים התחתונים ניתנים מחוט הסיקרא ולמטה. Damim hatachtonim nitanim mechut
hasikra ulemata. The below bloods would be below the red line. So
first of all, where's the red line? Second of all, what are
the above and what are the below? So above is a חטאת
Chatat for a בהמה, Behema, it's a חטאת, Chatat, that's actually at
the corners itself, and all other like large animals or sheep or
cows or whatever would be below the red line. עולה שלמים, Ola
shelamim, etc. Okay. Whereas אשם asham and so on. By the birds
it would be reversed. A bird חטאת chatas would be below and
a bird עולה olah would be above. Okay? So just know the
בהמה behemah thing and just reverse it by the bird. Okay? בהמה
behemah the only thing that would be above would be the חטאת,
chatas, everything else, עולה, olah, שלמים, shlamim, you know, תודה, toda, פסח,
pesach, whatever, אשם asham would all be below the line. Okay now,
where was this line? So the way the altar was created, I
mean here you get like a zoom in view. Okay, we could
kind of do a Google Maps and we could like... anyway, you
had an אמה amah here at the bottom, okay, this was the
יסוד, yesod, that was one אמה. amah. Then it went in a
little bit and went up five אמות, amos, okay, and that was
sort of like the next section, then went in a bit and
went
up...
what is it, four אמות? amos? I think? And then you had
the horns. Okay, so that's what it would look like
and so it would be ten, not counting the horns. And the
red line would be at five, so it would be at half,
so the red line would be here. Okay, now when you would
go up on the ramp,
I'll draw the ramp this way, when you would go up on
the ramp, okay, here's the כהן kohen going up the ramp. The
ramp would go all the way up if you had to stand
here at the top and put the stuff to burn on the
fire, right, up here. Okay, but if you want to be putting
the blood of the חטאת, chatas, you're going to get at a
like at a you know an access road or whatever an off-road
from the ramp and you come off here and this is what
we're talking about where
you'd come off here and you'd go around the סובב. sovev. Right,
the סובב sovev because this is an אמה amah inset, right you
see how this is like an אמה amah inset, so there'd be
an אמה, amah, an אמה's amah like a foot and a half,
for you to walk all around there. You see that's what insetting
it allows you to do. So when it says you come to
the סובב sovev and you walk around and you apply it the
blood up here actually. So if this is I think this is
four. Do you have one of those pictures in your Soncino or
whatever? No?
Can you give me a pic... no, nobody has a Soncino? I
mean whatever, the קורן? Koren?
Michael sent an email, let's see.
Yeah let's see, let's see if this has it. Just want to
make sure I'm pretty sure it's four not three. I just want
to make double check. Let's see if they have a picture here.
I think they do.
I'm not seeing a
picture. Alright, this is when you need pictures. Okay, anyway,
yeah well here they have a picture.
What?
Looks like yours.
Yeah it does look like mine. I just want to remember if
that's four or three from
the... alright let's keep on going, I'm not remembering if that's four
or three, should have checked that. Anyway, okay, so whatever it is,
I think it anyway here you're standing, okay, and you're putting the
blood up there. Now, so again, an אמה amah is about a
foot and a half. So this is about, so that's six, that's
like what, nine feet, okay,
and the thing is there, so if you're at the base here,
okay, a person is like what five feet or something, anyway, so
you're probably throwing the blood around like at this area and here
you're standing here and you're putting the blood, I think this might
be three. It might be five, I think it's one, five, three,
one to make a total of ten including the horns. That's what
I was trying to check. Anyway because that makes sense because then
you're standing here, that's like four and a half feet, that gives
you just the right type of height in order to be putting
the blood at the corners. So I'm pretty sure that's what it
is, it's one, five, three, one. Okay, anyway, so there you go.
So the חטאת chatas is above, really it's way up here, we're
going to discuss if it can include, can a חטאת chatas include
all of this, that's what we're going to discuss. Okay, but the
חטאת chatas is over there, the lower bloods are below that line.
All right, so let's take a look. So דתניא דמים עליונים ניתנים
מחוט הסיקרא ולמעלה דמים תחתונים ניתנים מחוט הסיקרא ולמטה דברי רבי רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר במה דברים אמורים בעולת העוף. detanya damim elyonim
nitnim michut hasikra ulemaalah damim tachtonim nitnim michut hasikra ulematah divrei Rabbi
Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon omer bameh devarim amurim beolas haof.
When can I consider doing a blood above the red line? When
you say above the red line, you're suggesting this entire area. That's
when you're doing a bird עולה. olah. Remember, a bird עולה olah
is... a חטאת chatas בהמה behemah is the only thing that goes
up here and a bird עולה. olah. So a bird עולה olah
can start anywhere from this line up. במה דברים אמורים בעולת העוף
אבל בחטאת בהמה היא עצמה נעשית על גופה של קרן. bameh devarim
amurim beolas haof aval bechatas behemah hi atzmah naasis al gufah shel
keren.
That you got to do at the corner itself. So I mean
obviously above the line, but a lot more specific than above the
line, don't tell me anything. anything here can be above the line.
No, if you're dealing with a חטאת, chatas, it's gotta be at
the corners
themselves. Okay. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abahu, מאי טעמא דרבי? mai
taama de-Rabbi? What's the reason of רבי? Rabbi? Because obviously the position
that it has to be at the corner itself, at the corner
itself is פשטא דפסוקים. pshata de-pesukim. The פסוקים pesukim say קרנות המזבח,
karnos ha-mizbe'ach, right? Where does רבי Rabbi get the idea that that
means, you know, that it could be any of this space? Of
course part of the question is, does קרן keren mean horn, or
does קרן keren mean corner, right? And if קרן keren means corner,
so then you could say anything here in the first אמה amah
off of the edge in either direction is considered a corner. But
so where does רבי Rabbi get this? So he
says: אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abahu, מאי טעמא דרבי? mai taama
de-Rabbi? What's the reason of רבי? Rabbi? דכתיב, de-ksiv,
the verse says וההראל ארבע אמות. ve-ha-har'el arba amos. וההראל, ve-ha-har'el, which
is a one of the words in the תנ"ך, Tanakh, particularly יחזקאל,
Yechezkel, for the מזבח mizbe'ach is ארבע אמות. arba amos. ומההראל ולמעלה,
u-mei-ha-har'el u-lemalah, and it goes on to describe it. Now, ארבע אמות
arba amos הוה דהוה? hu de-hava? Was it only four אמות? amos?
The מזבח mizbe'ach was a lot more than four אמות. amos. What
does it mean to say that it was four אמות? amos? So
אמר רבי אדא בר אהבה, Amar Rabbi Adda bar Ahava, מקום קרנות
ארבע. mekom karnos arba. No, it means that the corners are four
because each corner is an אמה amah by an אמה. amah. So
if you count the corner there are four אמות. amos. Okay, I
mean, you know, four אמות amos by one אמה, amah, but they're
four אמות, amos, four, you know, square אמות. amos. So the גמרא
Gemara says, מקום קרנות ארבע? mekom karnos arba? מקום קרנות ארבע הוה?
Mekom karnos arba hava? What? That's not a real four אמות. amos.
I mean each one is an אמה amah by an אמה, amah,
but it's not like a full if we're saying the מזבח mizbe'ach
is four אמות, amos, we don't, you know, it doesn't, that's just
like four, you know, single אמות. amos. It's not like a literal
four אמות amos height or four אמות amos width. So so אלא
אימא רשות קרנות ארבע. ella eima reshus karnos arba. No. So what
it means is is that the קרנות karnos take up four אמות
amos because if you start at the קרן, keren, again assuming I'm
getting this right that it's three over here, if you start at
the קרן keren and go all the way down, so that's four
אמות. amos. So when we say that the מזבח mizbe'ach is four,
we don't mean the whole מזבח, mizbe'ach, we mean the corners, and
we don't mean just these are four אמות, amos, we mean the
height of the corners, the effective space the corners take up is
from here if they go all the way down and this section
is three and the corners are one, that gives you a height
of four אמות. amos. So that's the basis of רבי. Rabbi. Did
I get it wrong? Is it four plus the corner?
There is a רש"י Rashi that says the four אמות amos down
from the bottom of the horn, which reaches to the red line.
Oh, oh I guess if you include this. Right. So that would
be true too. So that I was wondering about that actually. I
didn't, let me double check רש"י, Rashi, I didn't remember that.
It says the
height includes the horn.
That would be interesting.
It is true that רבי Rabbi says anything above the red line,
but that's particularly interesting that if you go like this and then
what? Does it go continue going straight down or then do you
shift to the corner here? How do you deal with this last
one אמה amah above the line that's actually not directly below the
horn, right? That would be a little bit bizarre that over here
would be considered the corner because it would be directly below the
horn, but closer to this corner actually wouldn't be the corner. So
I don't actually know. I'll double check that רש"י. Rashi. But you're
right, that four אמות amos would be the three אמות amos of
this section plus the one אמה amah above the line, not just
starting from the top of the horn, which still has this section
as three אמות. amos. So you are correct. Okay, but it is
an interesting question where on this lower section would be that last
אמה. amah. Let me just check that רש"י. Rashi. Hold on. אם
רשות הקרנות תופסת למטה
מהן ארבע אמות עד
החוט. Im reshus ha-karnos tofeseis lemata
mei-hen arba amos ad
ha-chut.
Yeah, you're right, רש"י Rashi says until this line. So that's really
fascinating that you could be over here because that's what it sounds
like, רבי Rabbi says anything above the line, and put it really
way below your feet and put it here and that's considered to
be the קרן. keren. But again, I do wonder if you would
have to then move to the actual edge if it's enough that
it's directly below that corner above. Okay, let's continue now in the
גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. תנן התם חוט
של סיקרא חוגרו באמצע. Tnan hasam chut shel sikra chogro ba-emtza.
So the again this red line would would belt it in the
middle להבדיל בין דמים העליונים ודמים התחתונים. lehavdil bein damim ha-elyonim ve-damim
ha-tachtonim. מנלן? Menalan? Where would you get this from? Meaning
where do you get the idea that conceptually it's there's a half
and that it's the top half versus the bottom half, meaning maybe
the חטאת chatas is on the corners and anything else is anywhere
on the altar like how do you conceptually where do you get
the idea that conceptually we divide it to a top half and
a bottom half. Okay. So אמר רב אחא בר רב קטינא, Amar
Rav Acha bar Rav Katina, שנאמר והייתה הרשת עד חצי
המזבח. she-ne'emar ve-haysa ha-reshes ad chatzi ha-mizbe'ach. The grillwork would be to
the middle of the of the altar. There'd be some external like
lattice work, you know, decorative. התורה ניתנה מחיצה להבדיל בין דמים העליונים
ודמים התחתונים. Ha-Torah nesna mechitzah lehavdil bein damim ha-elyonim ve-damim ha-tachtonim. Since
it says חצי המזבח, chatzi ha-mizbe'ach, what it is telling you is
that the purpose that lattice work, in addition to being decorative, would
divide it in half and conceptually there'd be blood that goes on
the top half and blood that goes on the bottom half. Okay,
so that's that. שירי הדם, Shirei ha-dam, the remnants of the blood
you would spill where, not on the west where you would do
by the inner חטאת, chatas, but on the south because you're coming
down here on the south. Okay, so that's that. שיירי הדם, She'arei
HaDam, the remnants of the blood, you would spill where? Not on
the west where you would do by the inner חטאת, Chatas, but
on the south because you're coming down here on the south. Okay.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, אל יסוד מזבח המזבח, El Yesod Mizbeach Hamizbeach,
זה יסוד דרומי. zeh Yesod Dromi. So when it says spill it
by the base, that's the southern base. אתה אומר Atah Omer זה
יסוד דרומי zeh Yesod Dromi או אינו אלא יסוד מערבי? o eino
ela Yesod Maaravi? Maybe it's the western base like we did when
you came from the inner חטאת? Chatos? וילמד סתום מן המפורש, Vilamed
satum min hamforash, and learn what is not explicit from that which
is explicit. Since by the inner חטאת Chatas it says that you
spill it, you know, פתח אהל מועד, Petach Ohel Moed, the opening,
you spill it at the base of the altar that's at the
opening of the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, which means as soon as
you walk out here, the first thing at the opening, of course,
is the western base. So that's explicit that it's the western base.
It says the opening of אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. So here too,
you should spill it where that spilled, at the western base. So,
אמרת, Amarta, וילמד ירידתו מן הכבש ליציאתו מן ההיכל. yilamid yeridato min
hakevesh liyetziaso min haheichal. Yes,
we are going to learn this from the inner חטאת, Chatos, but
not a blind application of the idea of, oh, western, western. But
conceptually, why by the inner חטאת Chatos do you spill it at
the western base? Because that's the first thing you hit when you
leave the, you know, the היכל. Heichal. So here too, the first
thing you hit when you come off of the altar is the
southern base. מה יציאתו מן ההיכל בסמוך לו,
אף ירידתו מן הכבש בסמוך לו. Mah yetziaso min haheichal besamuch lo,
af yeridato min hakevesh besamuch lo. So here too, that's why it
is. So it is here, it is the southern base, it is
not the western. So now the גמרא Gemara though says this actually
is a debate. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. Braisah. רבי
ישמעאל אומר, זה וזה יסוד מערבי. Rabbi Yishmael Omer, zeh vezeh Yesod
Maaravi.
Actually, both of them are the western base, like the גמרא's Gemara
הוה אמינא hava amina before. We know that the inner חטאת Chatas
is a western base, so therefore we're going to say this too
is learned from the inner חטאת Chatas and it's the western base.
Okay. רבי שמעון בן יוחאי אומר, Rabbi Shimon Ben Yochai Omer, זה
וזה יסוד דרומי, zeh vezeh Yesod Dromi,
they're both the southern base. Now, that's a strange idea. We understand
why this you would want to do the southern base, it's where
you come down of the altar. But here it says you do
it by the altar that's פתח אהל מועד, Petach Ohel Moed, so
that suggests that you face when you leave the אהל מועד. Ohel
Moed. So how would this ever translate into the southern base? So
that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to ask. בשלמא למאן דאמר זה
וזה יסוד מערבי, כסבר ילמד סתום מן המפורש. Bishlama leman de'amar zeh
vezeh Yesod Maaravi, kasavar yilamed satum min hamforash.
So the one that says they're both the west, you learn what's
unexplicit from what's explicit. And the same way the inner חטאת Chatas
is the west because that's what you hit when you leave the
היכל, Heichal, the outer חטאת Chatas will also be the west. Okay.
אלא למאן דאמר יסוד דרומי, זה וזה יסוד דרומי, Ela leman de'amar
Yesod Dromi, zeh vezeh Yesod Dromi, they're both the southern base, מאי
טעמא? mai ta'ama? How do you say that? How does it fit
the verse of where it says פתח אהל מועד? Petach Ohel Moed?
And what you hit when you leave פתח אהל מועד Petach Ohel
Moed from an inner חטאת Chatas is the western base. So אמר
רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, כסבר האי תנא כולי מזבח בצפון קאי,
kasavar hai tanna kulei mizbeach batzafon kai, לשון אחר כולי פתח בדרום
קאי. lashon acher kulei petach badarom kai. So it depends... it is
possible that you hit the southern base as soon as you leave.
How is that possible? Because again, because
here's...
where's the marker? I don't know what happened. I cover my markers
and they still dry out.
Supposed to be a special bag right there for ruining markers, why
I have to keep them secret. I had black
anyway, I must have lost it. I need
new colors. Anyway,
okay,
so, anyway, right, everything's have to be in the
north, right? We know that. Like the thing is slaughtered in the
north, right? And here's your פתח אהל מועד, Petach Ohel Moed, here's
your אולם Ulam whatever, here's your פתח, Petach, okay. So this is
directly centered. Where is the מזבח? Mizbeach? Now, normally we would assume
that the מזבח Mizbeach would be centered as well, okay, and then
you would come out and you would only really hit the western
base, right? That's what we would assume. But there's an opinion that
actually the entire מזבח, Mizbeach, not the ramp, would be in the
north. So if the entire מזבח Mizbeach would be in the north,
and therefore if the base goes like this, when you are coming
out, okay, now the doorway here, the door to this, would be
five אמות amot to the north and five אמות amot to the
south. It would be a ten אמה amah door. So if you
came out like in the northern part of that doorway, you'd hit
the western base. But if you came out in the southern part
of the doorway, and the entire altar here was in the north,
right, and you were coming out in the southern half of that
doorway, you would be hitting actually the western base... I mean the
southern base. Right, you see that? So if the altar was all
up in the north, and your door was half in the north...
and half in the south. If you came out from the south
end of that doorway, you would hit the southern base, you would
not be facing the face of the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay. So, כסבר
האי תנא כולה מזבח בצפון קאי, kasavar hai tana kula mizbeach bi-tzafon
kai, the entire מזבח mizbeach was in the צפון. tzafon. לשנא אחרינא
כולה פתח בדרום קאי, lishna acharina kula petach ba-darom kai,
or the entire פתח petach of the אולם ulam was in the
דרום. darom. Now that's not true, the entire פתח petach was not
in the דרום, darom, but at least half the פתח petach was
in the דרום. darom. Anyway, it's different ways of saying it, but
the basic point is, is that you would be possible to come
out, you know, in the lower half, in the southern half of
that doorway, and you would not be facing the face of the
מזבח. mizbeach. You'd be like along, you know, you'd be along, like
below the bottom of the מזבח, mizbeach, and the one thing that
you would be seeing would be the southern base. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues, תנא. tana. תנא דבי
רבי
ישמעאל,
tana
de-vei
Rabbi Yishmael, now the house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael taught, ברבי
שמעון בן יוחאי. be-Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai. So the house of רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that said that they would both be the west
taught in the name of רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai who said that they would both be in the דרום, darom,
right, that's the version we have, that רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabbi
Shimon ben Yochai says they would both be in the דרום. darom.
So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael taught that their opposing house said the
same thing they said. זה וזה יסוד מערבי. zeh ve-zeh yesod maaravi.
So רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai said it was
actually said it was all in the דרום darom and but when
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael taught the position of רבי שמעון בן יוחאי
Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai they had them say that it was both
in the west. They basically claimed that their opponents said the same
thing they said. Okay. וסימנך, ve-simanach,
the way to remember this is, משכו גברי לגברא. mashchu gavrei le-gavra.
The many people drew the few people towards them. The house of
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael was more numerous than the house of, you
know, of רבי שמעון בן יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai. So basically
majority rules. So they claimed not only are we more numerous and
we're right, when they actually told over the position of רבי שמעון
בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai again, one wonders if the גמרא
Gemara is saying that they intentionally misrepresented it or they actually just
understood them to be saying the same thing. But whatever. Anyway, according
to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael everybody agreed with them that it was
the west and not the דרום. darom. The idea that it's the
דרום darom for the inner חטאות chataot is a strange idea. You
could make it work, yes, if you put the whole מזבח mizbeach
in the צפון, tzafon, but it is the strangest of the possibilities.
Okay. So now we continue.
It
says
like
this. העולה, ha-ola, the עולה ola is קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, is
the holy of holies. The גמרא Gemara is going to ask, everything
we're listing now is קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, why does it specifically
repeat it by the עולה? ola? שחיטתה בצפון, shechitata ba-tzafon, and you
slaughter it in the צפון. tzafon. וקיבול דמה בכלי שרת בצפון, ve-kibul
dama bi-kli sharet ba-tzafon, and you catch the blood in the צפון.
tzafon. ודמה טעון שתי מתנות שהן ארבע. ve-dama teun shtei matanot she-hen
arba. You would put them at the
two,
you know, diagonal corners and at each corner you would sort of
have it hit on both sides. So that would be, here that's
like my picture, two that are four. Two here and two here,
whatever, so that would cover all four sides.
וטעונה הפשט וניתוח וכליל לאישים. ve-teuna hafshat ve-nituach ve-chalil la-ishim. You would
flay it, you would chop it up into pieces, and you would
completely burn it on the מזבח. mizbeach. What is the relevance of
it being קדשי קדשים? kodshei kodashim? This whole category is קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodashim. The simple point of קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is that
the stuff does not leave Temple grounds. If it's an עולה ola
it's all burned, even things that are eaten are only eaten on
Temple grounds, you know, they can't go even into the עזרת נשים,
ezras nashim, they can't leave עזרת ישראל, ezras yisrael, that's נאכלין לפנים
מן הקלעים. ne-echalin lifnim min ha-kela'im. And it's only eaten by male
כהנים, kohanim, they could have been בעלי מום, ba'alei mum, but only
male כהנים, kohanim, that was what we talked before. The other reference
for it being קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is that מעילה meila applies
to it. By שלמים shelamim there is a part מעילה meila applies
to it, the אימורין imurin that are burnt on the מזבח, mizbeach,
but fundamentally the קרבן korban as a whole is not קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodashim. Okay. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. עולה
מאי טעמא תני לה קדשי קדשים? ola mai taama tani lah kodshei
kodashim? Why does it explicitly say קדשי קדשים? kodshei kodashim? We're dealing
with all these קרבנות korbanot that are קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. משום
דלא כתיב קדשי קדשים הוא. mishum de-lo ksiv kodshei kodashim hu. Because
interesting, it is ironic. The עולה ola is the thing that is
fully burned. You know if we were asking what is the paradigm
קרבן korban that is all to God, that is the holy of
holies or whatever, we would say the עולה, ola, right, it's all
burned, but interestingly the פסוקים pesukim only use that term by like
a חטאת, chattat, they don't use that term by an עולה. ola.
So therefore the משנה Mishna wanted to emphasize that that was the
case. ודמה טעון שתי מתנות שהן ארבע, ve-dama teun shtei matanot she-hen
arba, two that are four. היכי עביד? heichi avid? How would you
do the blood? אמר רב amar Rav נותן וחוזר ונותן. nosen ve-chozer
ve-nosen. So actually right everybody agreed here if this is like the
you know the מזבח mizbeach you would do these two you know
diagonal corners. So two which are four means you throw at this
corner and you hit both sides. Actually, right, everybody agrees here if
this is like the altar, you want to do these two diagonal
corners. So you, two which are four means you throw at this
corner and you hit both sides here, and then you throw at
this corner and you hit both sides and that's four. So normally
the assumption two that is four is like it's one application, one
throwing, and it gets hits both sides. But רב Rav actually says
no. Actually, it means you would physically stand at two corners, but
when you would apply it, you would you would apply it separately.
You'd first apply it this side and then you'd apply it that
side. And then you go and apply it this side and apply
it that side. Okay, so who so which is strange. Like that's
never the way it's described. נותן וחוזר ונותן, noten vechozer venoten, you
literally apply it, you know, you stand at two corners, but you
apply it to each one of the sides of those corners separately.
ושמואל אמר מתנה אחת כמין גמא. u'Shmuel amar matana achat k'min gama.
No, it would be one application of blood, throwing of blood, like
a Greek gamma, okay, which is a, you know, which is a
like an L, essentially, okay, and that means you would throw it
and it would hit both sides.
נותן כמין גמא נותן. noten k'min gama noten. כתנאי, k'tannai, this is
a debate like a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. Here's the ברייתא. Baraita.
יכול יזרקנו זריקה אחת? yachol yizrekenu zerika achat? Maybe you just do
one application of blood, not at two opposite corners. תלמוד לומר סביב.
talmud lomar saviv. It says והמזבח יזרקנו סביב, ve'hamizbeach yizrekenu saviv, throw
it around about the altar. אי סביב, ei saviv, if it's around
about, יכול יקיפנו כחוט. yachol yakifennu kachut. Maybe you literally like, you
know, take your finger or whatever you do and you make a
whole like belt around the altar, you literally do it all around
the altar, right? So יכול יקיפנו כחוט, yachol yakifennu kachut, תלמוד לומר
וזרקו. talmud lomar v'zarko. You throw the blood. So you know, you
need a lot of blood to be throwing and getting every sort
of like reminds me when I'm trying to kosher for פסח, Pesach,
right? You gotta get every single part of the surface of the
counter. You need a lot of water if you're throwing it, it's
you're not going to be able to throw it and get it
all the way around, you know, the you know, the entire circumference
of the altar.
הא כיצד? ha keitzad? כמין גמא. k'min gama. Like a gamma. שתים
שהן ארבע shtayim shehen arba two that are four, which is what
שמואל Shmuel said. רבי ישמעאל אומר נאמר כאן סביב ונאמר להלן סביב.
Rabbi Yishmael omer ne'emar kan saviv v'ne'emar lehalan saviv. It says here
סביב saviv and it says over there סביב. saviv. Where's the over
there?
Oh, by the חטאת. chatat. מה להלן פיסוק וארבע מתנות, mah lehalan
pisuk v'arba matanot,
the same way by the חטאת chatat there are four separate applications,
אף כאן פיסוק וארבע מתנות, af kan pisuk v'arba matanot,
here too, they're each side is distinct and it's four separate applications.
So yes, you're at two corners, but at each corner, you don't
do one throwing, you do two throwings, one separate one for each
side.
Okay, אי מה להלן ארבע מתנות על ארבע קרנות אף כאן ארבע
מתנות על ארבע קרנות. ei mah lehalan arba matanot al arba kranot
af kan arba matanot al arba kranot. Maybe here too, you put
it at the horns. You don't do it at the, you know,
you don't do it at the lower half.
So אמרת עולה טעונה יסוד. amarta olah te'una yesod. No, cause by
the עולה olah we learned earlier that not only is the remnants
built out at the base, but the application of blood has to
be on a place of the altar that there is a protruding
base below it.
וקרן מזרחית דרומית לא היה לה יסוד. v'keren mizrachit dromit lo haya
lah yesod. And the southeast corner did not have a base. So
here, okay, I guess if we're using my nice big 4D one
here.
Okay, if that's what this looks like. If this is east, north,
here's, you know, here's where you walk in. Okay, so the southeast
corner here the base did not protrude. Okay, we're going to actually
see that the way it would have looked is like this. This
base like wrapped around here and this base wrapped around here and
this whole section
was
like how am I going to draw that? Anyway, that whole section
was like inset,
okay.
So
the base sort of came out here and came out there. Obviously,
it had obviously it wasn't floating in mid-air. Okay, here maybe that's
the right look. Okay, that's there. There you go. Then now that's
clear. Okay, so, okay, it did not have a protruding base at
this southeast corner. So therefore, it's you can you would do it
here and here, okay, because those would get you two that are
four, but you could not do it at all four corners because
you couldn't do it at this corner because this corner did not
have a base, a protruding base. Okay, so even though רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael says... That you have to learn from the application of
the חטאת Chatas that you have it on separate walls, you don't
do, you don't do one throwing, you have a separate application on
each wall, you can't do it at each corner, you do it
at this corner too and this corner too, because this did not
have a base. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says now, why
not?
So here David anticipated this. Okay, וכאן מזרחית דרומית לא היה יסוד.
V'chan mizrachis dromis lo haya yesod. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why not?
אמר רב אלעזר Amar Rav Elazar says רב אלעזר, Rav Elazar, אמר
רב אלעזר, Amar Rav Elazar, לפי שלא היתה
בחלקו של טורף lefi shelo haysa bechelko shel toreif because it wasn't
in the portion of the of the like the devourer. It says
בנימין זאב יטרף, Binyamin ze'ev yitrof, Benjamin is a devouring wolf. Okay,
and from there we learn בבקר יאכל עד ולערב יחלק שלל. baboker
yochal ad ula'erev yechalek shalal. So the idea that like the, you
know, this is very anthropomorphic, but at least it's anthropomorphic sort of
more about animal than about God, but you know, the altar rather
than God consuming and the altar consuming, whatever, the altar is like
this animal consuming its prey. The prey are the animal that you
put on the altar. And the idea is that this was understood
that since this is how בנימין Binyamin is described, that the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the מזבח Mizbeach in particular was in the section
of בנימין Binyamin where it's devouring its prey. But we're also going
to understand that יהודה, Yehuda, the section of יהודה, Yehuda, which was
the, you know, ירושלים Yerushalayim is fundamentally in the section of יהודה,
Yehuda, was the entire בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash up to the altar.
So basically, if you imagine, right, here you've got the entire בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Here's the, you know, here's the עזרת ישראל, Ezras
Yisrael, I mean where they can stop where they can walk, here's
the עזרת כהנים, Ezras Kohanim, here's the, you know, and obviously whatever,
like this,
here's the עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. Okay, you got the whole בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash starting in the east. All of this is in
the חלק cheilek of יהודה. Yehuda. Okay, so this is all יהודה,
Yehuda, okay, all יהודה Yehuda until you get to the altar. And
at the altar is where בנימין Binyamin starts. Okay, and בנימין Binyamin
the חלק cheilek was in בנימין, Binyamin, but because, so why not
have a base? But because we understand that the חלק cheilek of
יהודה Yehuda went all the way up to the altar and went
in a little bit here and a little bit here. Okay, so
I guess here if you look at it up here at this
picture, right, this is all the חלק cheilek of יהודה Yehuda and
you would have thought
that
it should stop at the altar itself, right? But what it should,
but although I mean if this is like the base here, like
let's say that that's the base, it should stop at the altar,
but it doesn't, but he actually goes and he gets a little
bit here and a little bit here and that is included in
the חלק cheilek of יהודה. Yehuda. And because that's included in the
חלק cheilek of יהודה Yehuda and we want the whole altar to
be in the portion of בנימין, Binyamin, this piece which is יהודה
Yehuda does not have a base of the altar. Okay, alright, so
let's take a look. ומפני מה לא היה יסוד בחלקו של טורף?
Umipnei mah lo haya yesod bechelko shel toreif? דאמר
רב שמואל בר יצחק מזבח אוכל בחלקו של
יהודה אמה. D'amar
Rav Shmuel bar Yitzchak mizbeach ochel bechelko shel
Yehuda ama. It was an אמה amah into the portion
of יהודה, Yehuda, the
base of the altar. Okay, so אמר רבי לוי בר חמא אמר
רבי חנינא רצועה היתה יוצאת מחלקו של יהודה. Amar Rabbi Levi bar
Chama amar Rabbi Chanina retzuah haysa yotzes mechelko shel Yehuda. So they
sort of call it a line would go out is that really
the
portion
of יהודה Yehuda would
end right at the base of the altar, right at the at
the east of the base, but a little extra would go in
here and a little extra would go in there in an area
where the base should have been and that's and יהודה Yehuda gets
a little piece of that. I'm sure some rabbi could do a
wonderful sermon about the significance of that. But anyway, okay, מחלקו של
יהודה ונכנסת בחלקו של בנימין. mechelko shel Yehuda venichneses bechelko shel Binyamin.
והיה בנימין הצדיק מצטער עליה בכל יום Vehaya Binyamin hatzadik mitzta'er aleha
bechol yom לנוטלה, lenotla,
and בנימין Binyamin the righteous one, so here you see it seems
like it's very avaricious or something, oh he wanted to take something
away from יהודה, Yehuda, but because it was sort of like I
don't I guess driven by religious desire, somehow it's, you know, it
phrases as בנימין הצדיק. Binyamin hatzadik. Here we said like oh this
is terrible like a little piece of that section of where the
מזבח mizbeach should be in my section it's in יהודה's Yehuda section.
I want that all to be in my section. שנאמר shene'emar as
it says חופף עליו כל היום ובין כתפיו שכן. chofeif alav kol
hayom uvein keseifav shachein. So like, you know, the divine presence like
hovers over it all day and dwells between like the shoulders of
בנימין. Binyamin. So somehow that sense like hovering over it, which I
think פשט pshat of the פסוקים pesukim sort of is like God's
presence is hovering over is like בנימין Binyamin is hovering over, you
know, and he like just wants to get it all like he
you know why is it that a little piece of the space
where the מזבח mizbeach should be is in יהודה's Yehuda section? ונעשה
לפיכך Vena'asa leficach
and because he so much wanted... To be in his section, you
know, it's so funny because nowadays obviously so many you know fights
are you know wars are because of people wanting holy places to
be, you know, in their land.
So but here you know it says oh it's all like religiously
driven and it's for the right reasons. זכה בנימין הצדיק ונעשה אושפיזין
לקדוש ברוך הוא. Zacha Binyamin hatzadik v'na'aseh ushpizin l'Kadosh Baruch Hu. And
therefore he became like the host of God, that God's presence was
in his land, שנאמר ובין כתפיו שכן, shene'emar u'vein k'teifav shachein, and
God's presence dwells between his shoulders. You know, so also maybe the
idea of like between the shoulders is you know a little bit
inset, it's not flat, I don't know, there's some imagery that's parallel.
I also don't fully get this because you know
because it seems like the מזבח mizbeach was already there. So what
was he זוכה zocheh that he was made a host of the
divine presence? The divine presence was already there before he was מצטער,
mista'eir, just the normal way it was divided, you know, had it
this way. So what did he gain extra because of this anguish
that he had? Anyway,
okay. שכן מיתיבי, sheken meitivi, now let's read one more line, I'll
ask you on this. עולת העוף כיצד הייתה נעשית הייתה מו... olat
ha'of keitzad hayta na'asit hayta mo... you know, let's just end here,
let's not go on. Okay. So anyway,
we'll pick up with this tomorrow, but this is why that corner
right there did not have it, because that was in יהודה's Yehuda
portion, and we want to understand that the entire place of the
of the מזבח, mizbeach, and also, by the way, this is ובין
כתפיו שכן, u'vein k'teifav shachein, you know, which this is obviously, maybe
that's also the ובין כתפיו, u'vein k'teifav, like this is the head
and the top and the place where actually the שכינה shechina is,
you know, which is a little bit lower, like it's between the
shoulders, right, the place of the קודש קדשים, kodesh kodashim, obviously that's
much more in בנימין's Binyamin חלק. chelek. So יהודה Yehuda and בנימין
Binyamin basically split it, you know, down the middle, so there was
ירושלים Yerushalayim was an international city. Okay. And somehow, anyway, and that's
why you did not put it at the at the southeastern corner.
So we'll end with this for now.